Register of the Hugh Gibson papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SUBJECT FILE, 1902-1955 (Boxes 79-97)
  - League of Nations, Geneva
    - Protocol for the Pacific Settlement of International Disputes. Draft submitted by the First and Third Committees to the Assembly, October 1, 1924
    - Special Commission for the Preparation of a Draft Convention on the Private Manufacture of Arms and Ammunition and of Implements of War, 1927-1928
    - Temporary Mixed Commission for the Reduction of Armaments - Proceedings of the 1st session, Geneva, July 7, 1924
  - Lebrun, Albert
  - "The Lesson of the Day" (in Harper's Weekly of, October 10, 1857)
  - La libre Belgique, Brussels, nos. 21, 30, 34, 36, 37, 38, 42, 46, 52, 53 (2 copies), 56, 1915
  - Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, "The Wind of Privation or the Sun of Mercy?", December 24, 1940
  - Loeb, James
  - Louvain Library, 1928
  - McCarthy, Joseph
  - Marshall, E. Newell
  - Mason, Frank
  - Miscellanea
  - Moffat, Jay Pierrepont
  - Morand, Paul (talk on Gibson)
  - Nam, General Cesare
  - National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies, N.Y., 1940-1943
  - National Council of Churches of Christ (from the files of the Committee on Un-American Activities - U.S. Congress. House of Representatives)
  - Das neue Europa, Berlin, 1932 January-February-March
  - Paderewski, Ignace Jan (Box 93)
  - Pan American Union, Washington, D.C. (Barrett, John, Director General), 1920
  - Paul-Boncour, Joseph
  - Pearson, Drew
  - Pecher, Charles, 1940-1941
  - Pegler, Westbrook
  - Permanent Court of International Justice - American reservations to
  - Pierce, Daniel T. [See: American Red Cross]
  - Poland [See also: Durand, E. F.; Eastern Galicia; Honeij, James A.; Interallied Mission to Poland; Klopstock, Paul; Upper Silesia]
    - General, 1920-1921
    - Economic situation. Annual Report of American Trade Commissioner, June 1921
    - Financial transactions - Romania, October 10, 1939
    - Relief
      - World War I [See also: Russian Red Cross in Poland]
        - General
        - British Committee for Relief in Poland
        - Methodist Mission (activities in Poland under attack)
      - World War II
        - General
        - Correspondence and memoranda of conversations of Gibson, 1940
  - Poraj, L., "The Proteest of the Slave-Soul,", 1919
  - Provisional Intergovernmental Committee for the Movement of Migrants from Europe, Geneva
    - General, 1952-1955
    - Speeches by Gibson, 1952-1954
  - Reid, Frank A. (Box 94)
  - Reyntiens, Guy N.
  - Roberts, Cecil
  - Rocky Mountain Club, N.Y., 1919
  - Rogers Bill (on the reorganization of the Consular and Diplomatic Services)
    - Addresses by Charles E. Hughes; Robert Lansing, and J. Butler Wright
    - Amendments, proposals
    - Anecdotes regarding ministers and diplomats
    - Correspondence of Gibson
      - Beal, Boylston A., 1923
      - Bliss, Robert Woods, 1922-1924
      - Carroll, Joseph W., 1923
      - Castle, William R., Jr., 1922-1923
      - Daniels, Thomas L., 1923
      - Dearing, Fred Morris, 1921-1924
      - Dennis, Lawrence, 1923
      - Dodge, H. Percival, 1923
      - Dolbeare, Frederick R., 1923
      - Einstein, Lewis, 1923
      - Fletcher, Henry P., 1921-1923
      - Grant-Smith, Ulysses, 1919-1924
      - Grew, Joseph C., 1919-1924
      - Gunther, Franklin M., 1925
      - Hall, Barton, 1923
      - Hoover, Herbert, 1921
      - Hughes, Charles Evans, 1923
      - Hugins, C. R., 1920
      - Jay, Augustus Peter, 1923-1924
      - Johnson, Stewart, 1923
      - Lane, Arthur Bliss, 1919-1924
      - Madden, Martin B., 1923 (Box 95)
      - Magruder, Alexander R., undated
      - Meyer, Cord, 1923
      - Newson, H. Dorsey, 1923
      - O'Laughlin, John Callan, 1923
      - Phillips, William, 1923
      - Richardson, R. Gilmore, 1923
      - Robbins, Warren D., 1921-1923
      - Rogers, John Jacob, 1919-1924
      - Ruddock, Albert B., 1919-1920
      - Schalk(?), H. A., 1924
      - Shaw, G. Howland, 1923
      - Stowell, Ellery C., 1918
      - White, John Campbell, 1923
      - Whitehouse, Sheldon, 1923
      - Williamson, Harold L., 1923
      - Wilson, Charles S., 1923
      - Wilson, Hugh R., 1919-1923
      - Wilson, Verne, Jr., 1923
      - Winslow, Alan F., 1923
      - Wright, J. Butler, 1919-1923
    - Correspondence of Secretary of State Charles E. Hughes (released for the press, November 9, 1922)
    - Data on foreign service's total strength
    - Departmental order no. 295 (Department of State), June 9, 1924
    - Executive Order no. 4022, June 7, 1924
    - Memoranda (mostly by Gibson)
    - Printed matter
    - Reports, studies (Box 96)
      - By Gibson
      - By others
    - Text of House Resolution 6357
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Mrs. Franklin D.)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Mrs. Theodore, Jr.)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D.
  - Russian Red Cross in Poland, 1921
  - Sadikowa Choupaz, Natalie
  - Schmidt-Chevalier, Curt
  - Schofield, Rear Admiral, "Freedom of the Seas,", 1921 December 21
  - Sims, Admiral William S.
  - Sino-Japanese War, 1932
  - Smith, Bedell
  - Soviet Union
    - General, 1920-1924
    - Agriculture [See: CORRESPONDENCE, Rickard, Edgar, August 22, 1925]
    - Foreign relations - Germany
  - Spaak, Paul Henri
  - Spain
  - Stalin, Joseph
  - Strother, French
  - Switzerland [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Martin, William]
  - Thomas, Lowell
  - Thompson, Dorothy (Mrs. Sinclair Lewis), "The New Patriotism Is Peace: Third and Last Article in Which Women from Many Lands Make Their Pleas,", 1930
  - Toynbee, Arnold J.
  - Turkey - Entry to the League of Nations, 1932
  - Tyler, Royall
  - United States
    - General
    - Armed forces, 1923
    - Army
      - American Expeditionary Forces, 1918
      - Headquarters Third Corps Area [See also: BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, Officers' Reserve Corps], 1924-1925
      - Intelligence, 1918
      - Training manual, 1923
    - "Behold the Flag," by Ignatius I. Murphy
    - Comptroller General
    - Department of Justice
    - Department of State
      - General
      - Commercial attaches
      - Embassies - London
      - Foreign Service School
      - United Nations Affairs Division
      - Legations - Berne (Office of the military attache), 1918
    - Department of the Treasury
    - Elections, 1932
    - Financial situation, 1932
    - Foreign relations
      - General - Post World War II era
      - Argentina, 1920
      - Belgium, 1918
      - Cuba, 1903
      - France, 1918
      - Great Britain, 1911-1941
      - Latin America, 1909-1911 (Box 97)
      - Netherlands, 1921
      - Poland, 1919(?)
      - Soviet Union, 1920-1923
      - Switzerland, 1918
    - Foreign Relations Committee, 1917-1918
    - World War I
      - Moral preparadness
      - Treatment of prisoners of war
  - Upper Silesia - Plebiscite of, 1921 March 20
    - General
    - Reports by Gibson
  - Upton, Charles S., "Peace? Why Not?", 1942
  - Vacuum Oil Company, N.Y. [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Maguire, J. J.], 1916-1919
  - Walter Hines Page School of International Relations, N.Y.
  - Wheeler, Post and Hallie Ermine Rives
  - White, William Allen
  - Whitlock, Brand [See: Belgium, World War I, German rule and actrocities]
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman
  - Wile, Frederic William
  - Williams, William Carlos
  - Wilson, Alexander, Why a New League of Nations Will Not Succeed in Enforcing a Permanent Peace in an Uncivilized World, 1944
  - Wilson, Hugh R.
  - Wilson, Woodrow
  - Wolf, Otto
  - Wood, Leona P. - Correspondence re her request for birthdates and a few lines for the "Friendship Calendar" (birthday book) she is preparing for Gibson, 1909
  - World War I
    - Allied intervention in Russia
    - Debts payments
    - France
    - Germany
    - Great Britain
    - Pamphlets (mostly Belgian, some French)
    - Poland
    - Reports by Gibson, 1917 August 21 - 1918 April 16
  - Yale University
  - Young Women's Christian Associations
  - Yugoslavia
- DIPLOMATIC POSTS FILE, 1908-1938 (Boxes 98-101)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and speeches, arranged alphabetically by name of country where Hugh Gibson was assigned in the course of his foreign service career.
  - Belgium (Brussels), 1914-1916; 1927-1933; 1937-1938 (Box 98)
    - Appointment as Ambassador
      - 1927
        - General
        - Congratulations sent to Hugh and Ynes Gibson
      - - Congratulations sent to Hugh and Ynes Gibson, 1937
    - Clubs
    - Correspondence with Embassy
      - General, 1927-1930
      - Groves, J. Philip, 1930-1933
      - Mayer, Ferdinand L., 1931
      - Wilson, Warden McK., 1930
      - Woodward, Stanley, 1932-1933
    - Embassy compound and servants
    - Evaluation of State and other Departments' officials
    - German accusations against Gibson, 1918
    - Miscellaneous
    - Resignation, 1933
    - Speeches
  - Brazil (Rio de Janeiro), 1933-1937 (Box 99)
    - General
    - Appointment as Ambassador, 1933
    - Clubs
    - Correspondence - In and outgoing telegrams, 1933-1935
    - Frost, Mr., Counselor of the Embassy
    - Memoranda on U.S.-Brazil relations and U.S. Latin American policy
    - Speeches
    - Trade agreement between Brazil and the U.S., 1935
  - Cuba (Havana), 1911-1913
  - France (Paris), 1918
    - General
    - Assignment as First Secretary, 1918
    - Correspondence - In and outgoing telegrams
      - 1918 March-July
      - 1918 July-November
    - Miscellaneous
  - Honduras (Tegucigalpa), 1908-1909
  - Luxemburg (Brussels, stationed in), 1927-1933; 1937-1938
  - Poland (Warsaw), 1919-1924 (Box 100)
    - General
    - Accountant of Legation, John Weber
    - Accounts
      - General
      - Telegram account
    - Clubs [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Grodski, Stanislaw]
    - Correspondence
      - With Polish officials, 1921-1924
      - With the Secretary of State, 1919-1923
    - Guarantee Trust Company of New York - Contract with the Polish Government, 1921
    - Guest lists
    - Invitations
      - Received by Gibson
      - Sent out by Gibson
    - Legation compound and servants
    - Miscellaneous
    - Memoranda
      - For conversations with Polish officials
      - Re the Frank Morse case, 1923-1924
    - Polish Red Cross - Honorary Diploma confered upon Gibson, 1921
    - Relief work
      - Assistance extended
        - To individuals
        - To Russians in Poland [See also: SUBJECT FILE, Russian Red Cross in Poland]
        - To the intelligentsia
      - Correspondence
        - With Philip S. Baldwin, 1921
        - With Walter L. Brown, 1920
        - With Herbert Hoover, 1920
        - With Cyril J. C. Quinn, 1920-1921
        - With various relief groups and organizations
    - Reports (Box 101)
      - Re Paderewski's return [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Dulles, Allen, November 20, 1919; Hoover, Herbert, and House, Edward M., April 29, 1919; and Wilson, Woodrow, July 18, 1920]
      - Weekly Political Reports to the Secretary of State
        - 1921
        - 1922
        - 1923
        - 1924
    - Request for increase in contingent fund due to higher cost of living, 1924
    - Secretaries of Legation
      - Boal, Pierre de L.
      - Moffat, Jay Pierrepont
    - Telegrams, 1919 October - 1923 January
    - Transfer to Switzerland, 1924
    - Travel within the country
  - Switzerland (Bern), 1924-1927
    - Appointment as Ambassador [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Ambrose, W. H.], 1924
    - Correspondence with Lucile Atcherson, 1926
    - Invitations, received and sent out
    - Memoranda
    - Miscellaneous
    - Transfer to Belgium, 1927
- DISARMAMENT CONFERENCES FILE, 1926-1933 (Boxes 102-121)
  Charts, correspondence, graphs, memoranda, minutes of meetings, printed matter, reports, and studies, arranged chronologically by conference. As the series of disarmament conferences was an ongoing process, with conferences adjourning to await the outcome of others, some overlap could not be avoided.
  - Conference on the Limitation of Armament, Cannes, France, 1922 (Box 102)
  - Conference for the Supervision of the International Trade in Arms and Ammunition and in Implements of War, Geneva, 1925
  - Preparatory Commission for the General Disarmament Conference [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Murray, George D.], 1926-1932
    - General
      - Outline of the positions of the leading countries for and against budgetary limitations, 1931
      - Papers put together by Gibson (32 indexed documents)
    - 1st session, 1926 May
      - Instructions for the American delegation
      - Speeches
    - 2nd session, 1926 September
      - Correspondence
      - Sub-Commission B
    - 3rd session (4th session, November), 1927 March
      - Documents
      - List of delegates
      - Official report
      - Speeches
    - 5th session, 1928 March
      - Anglo-French Agreement
      - Correspondence
        - With other delegations
        - With the Secretary of State
      - Memoranda
      - Press clippings
      - Speeches
      - Telegrams, March 12-28
    - 6th session
      - First Part (adjourned May 6 to await the outcome of the London Naval Conference, 1930), 1929 April
        - General
        - Adjournment
        - Correspondence
          - Between Herbert Hoover and J. Ramsay MacDonald
          - Of Gibson
            - Congratulations and proposals sent by various individuals and peace organizations
            - Miscellaneous
            - With other delegations
            - With the Secretary of State
        - Documents
          - France
          - Great Britain
          - Turkey
        - Memoranda (Box 103)
          - General
          - Of conversations
        - Press clippings [See also: Memoranda, General]
        - Report by Frank B. Kellogg
        - Speeches
          - By Gibson
          - By others
        - Telegrams
          - Received
            - April-May
            - June-September
          - Sent out, April-May
      - Second Part, 1930 November
        - Commendation of advisors attached to the American delegation
        - Correspondence
          - Congratulations and proposals sent by various individuals and peace organizations
          - With other delegations
          - With Norman Armour, 1930 November - 1931 April
          - With William Castle
          - With the Secretary of State
        - Documents (Box 104)
        - Instructions for Gibson
        - Invitations received from other delegations
        - List of delegates
        - Memoranda
        - Miscellaneous
        - Press clippings (including bound volume) [See also: Correspondence with Norman Armour]
        - Speeches
        - Telegrams
          - Received, November 3-December 8
          - Sent out, November 5-December 9
    - Further talks and negotiations [See also: 6th session, Second Part, Correspondence with Norman Armour], 1931-1932 (Box 105)
      - Memoranda
        - General
        - Of conversations, 1931 September
      - Notes and suggestions regarding budget limitation, 1931 April 21
      - Press clippings
      - Statement by Gibson, 1931 September 7
      - Telegrams between the Secretary of State and
        - London embassy, 1931 January-November
        - Rome embassy, 1931 February - 1932 January
        - Other embassies and legations, 1931 June-November
  - Tripartite Naval Conference, Geneva, 1927 (Box 106)
    - General
    - Coolidge Proposal calling for the conference, February 10
    - Correspondence between the United States, Great Britain, Japan, France and Italy
    - Data, maps
    - Delegations - United States
    - Department of the Navy. General Board Report
    - Informal meeting of delegates held at the Hotel Beau Rivage in Viscount Saito's Rooms, July 6
    - Memoranda of conversations, June-July
    - Press clippings [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Dulles, Allen, November 14, 1927]
    - Speeches
    - Telegrams
      - Received, February 3-August 5
      - Sent out (Box 107)
        - February 14-July 15
        - July 16-August 5
  - London Naval Conference, 1929-1931
    - General
    - Anglo-American policies
    - Anglo-French-Italian Naval Agreement, 1931 March
    - Congratulations and proposals sent by various individuals and peace organizations [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, American Friends Service Committee]
    - Data
    - Delegations - American
      - General
      - Secretariat memoranda
      - Tentative plan
    - Directory
    - Documents (Box 108)
      - General
      - France
      - Great Britain
      - Italy
      - Japan
    - First Committee - Meetings and reports, 4.0 folders
    - Fourth plenary session, February 11 (Box 109)
    - Franco-Italian negotiations, 1930-1931
    - Memoranda
      - General
      - Of conversations
      - Sent to other governments
    - Miscellaneous
    - Naval intelligence reports and statistics
    - Preliminary talks and negotiations, 1929
      - General
      - Anglo-American understanding
      - Anglo-French conversations (including accord of, 1928)
      - Convocation of Powers signatory to the Washington Treaty - Correspondence, October-December
      - Memoranda of conversations
      - Telegrams sent to the Secretary of State from
        - London embassy, June-August
        - Paris embassy, November-December
    - Press clippings (Box 110)
    - Press communiques
    - Printed material
    - Secretariat notices
    - Speeches
    - Subcommittees reports
    - Submarines - The question of their abolition
    - Summaries of the British and French press
    - Telegrams (Box 111)
      - Received
        - 1930 January 11-February 9
        - February 10-February 25
        - February 26-March 16
        - March 17-April 3
        - April 4-April 20
      - Sent (Box 112)
        - To American embassy, Tokyo, 1930 January 21-April 11
        - To American embassies in Paris and in Rome, and to the Secratary of State, October 14-November 6
        - To the Secretary of State, January 17-April 14
      - Summary of telegrams exchanged on the subject of naval armaments since May 27, 1929
    - Treaty
  - General Disarmament Conference, Geneva, 1930-1933 (Box 113)
    - General
    - Agreement of Understanding and Cooperation between the Four Western Powers, 1932 December 11
    - Appointment of Gibson as delegate, 1932 January 4
    - Armaments Year Book. General and Statistical Information in regard to Land, Naval and Air Armaments, 1932
    - Correspondence
      - Congratulations and proposals sent by various individuals and peace organizations [See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Adams, Jane and Glenn, Otis F.]
      - With Norman Armour, 1932 April-July
      - With Walter E. Edge, 1932 May-June
      - With John W. Garrett, 1932 June-July
      - With other delegations, 1932
    - Delegations - American - Sick reports
    - Diaries
      - Of Gibson (minutes and memoranda of meetings)
      - Of Jay Pierrepont Moffat
    - Documents (Box 114)
      - Belgium
      - Czechoslovakia
      - Denmark
      - France
        - General [See also: Preparatory Commission, Correspondence with Norman Armour]
        - Budget, 1931-1932
      - Germany
      - Great Britain
      - Greece
      - Hungary
      - Italy
      - Japan
      - Latin American states
      - Norway [See: CORRESPONDENCE, Philip Hoffman]
      - Romania
      - Turkey
      - Series of League of Nations Publications
        - General
          - 1932 January-October
          - 1932 November - 1933 April (Box 115)
          - 1933 May (Box 116)
          - 1933 June-July (Box 117)
        - Particulars with regard to the position of armaments in the various countries
          - 1931
          - 1932
    - Hoover's proposal
      - Release by Gibson, 1932 June 22
      - Reactions - Italy
    - Instructions for Gibson from Secretary of State, Henry L. Stimson
    - Interview of Norman H. Davis, 1932 April 26
    - Journal, nos. 4, 5, 6, 7, and 115, 1932 February and July
    - Memoranda (Box 118)
      - General, 3.0 folders
      - From Henry Stimson to Gibson
      - From William Castle to Gibson
      - Of conversations
        - General
        - Regarding Germany's return to the conference
      - Of meetings of the American delegation
      - Personal matters
    - Miscellaneous
    - Naval aspects
      - France
      - Great Britain
      - United States
    - Official entertaining allowance
    - Official Guide
    - Press clippings (Box 119)
    - Press conference of William Castle, 1932 January 14
    - Press reviews
    - Printed matter
    - Reports, studies
    - Resolutions
    - Speeches
      - By Gibson
        - 1932
        - 1933
        - Not delivered
      - By others
    - Statement, 1932 April 30
    - Telegrams exchanged with the Secretary of State or other American embassies (Box 120)
      - Received
        - 1930 December - 1932 January
        - 1932 February-April
        - 1932 May-July 15
        - 1932 July 16 - 1933 January 27
      - Sent
        - 1931 January - 1932 January
        - 1932 February-March
        - 1932 April-May (Box 121)
        - 1932 June-July 15
        - 1932 July 16-October 29
        - 1932 November - 1933 January
    - Transcripts of telephone conversations
    - Three Powers (United States, Great-Britain, France) - Meetings and points of understanding, 1932 June
- HUGH GIBSON, 1883-1954 FILE (Boxes 122-126)
  Excerpts from Hugh Gibson's correspondence, diaries, and writings used or considered for publication in Hugh Gibson, 1883-1954 by Perrin C. Galpin, editor, arranged chronologically from 1908 to 1954. The book, published by the Belgian American Educational Foundation, Inc., N.Y. in 1956, was made up of extracts from Gibson's letters and anecdotes from his friends, with an introduction by Herbert Hoover and a foreword by Perrin C. Galpin, editor.
  - Book (Box 122)
    - Correspondence and other material related to the publication of the book
    - Galley proofs
    - Typewritten carbon copy
  - Excerpts from Gibson's correspondence, diaries and writings
    - Typewritten carbon copies
      - 1908-1909
      - 1910-1912
      - 1913-1916
      - 1917 (Box 123)
      - 1918
      - 1919
      - 1920-1921
      - 1922-1927
      - 1928-1929 (Box 124)
      - 1930-1933
      - 1934-1938
      - 1939-1945
      - 1946-1954
    - Typescripts and carbon copies (duplicates)
      - 1908-1910
      - 1911-1913
      - 1914-1916
      - 1917 (Box 125)
      - 1918
        - January-June
        - July-December
      - 1919
        - January-May
        - June-December
      - 1920
      - 1921-1923 (Box 126)
      - 1924-1928
      - 1929-1933
      - 1934-1954
- CLIPPINGS, 1902-1950 (Boxes 127-138)
  - 1902-1903; 1918; 1922-1924 (Box 127)
  - 1912-1920 (Box 128)
  - 1926 (Box 129)
  - 1927 (Boxes 130-131)
  - 1928 (Box 132)
  - 1929 (Boxes 133-134)
  - 1930 (Box 135)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 136)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 137)
  - 1936-1950 (Box 138)
- CARD FILE, 1908-1914 (Box 139)
  Sorted index card notes of people mentioned in Hugh Gibson's letters to his mother, with corresponding dates.
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, 1906-1956 (Boxes 140-152, on shelf)
  Albums, autograph and guest books, certificates, checkbooks, desk calendars, diplomas, medals, note books, and scrapbooks, arranged alphabetically by type.
  - Certificates of appointment (Box 140)
    - As ambassador
      - Poland, 1919
      - Switzerland, 1924
      - Belgium, 1927 and 1937
      - Brazil, 1933
      - Luxemburg, 1937
    - As delegate to the Sixth Session of the Preparatory Commission for the Disarmament Conference, Second Part, Geneva, 1930 November 6
    - As a Colonel of Military Intelligence in the Army of the United States, 1931 and 1936
  - Certificates of gratitude and admiration
    - From the Association of Polish Societies
    - From a Committee of Poles, including I. Paderewski
    - From Herbert Hoover to Gibson as a member of the Food Mission, 1947
  - Certificate from the Vatican, 1947
  - Certificate from the Munson S.S. Lines
  - Certificate from the PanAm Airlines, 1933